welcome to the Austria radio show the
Astoria radio show is brought to you by
WWE area magazine comm professor Jordan
Peterson is a clinical psychologist
licensed in Massachusetts and Ontario
he's also a professor at the University
of Toronto and has been so since 1998
professor Peterson is currently
interested in the formal assessment and
theoretical nature of self-deception
construing it as the voluntary failure
of exploration rather than as repression
he's also doing experimental work on
creativity achievement personality
narrative and motivation your host for
the next hour will be guy Lee
welcome to this edition of Astraea
magazine and web radio we're delighted
to have here with us
clinical psychologist professor Jordan
Peterson he's going to be telling us
about his amazing book maps of meaning
now first of all professor Peterson
welcome how are you good nice to be here
great could you please tell us a bit
first of all about your background well
I'm a clinical psychologist trained at
McGill University I've been working as a
professor since 1992 I taught at Harvard
University in the psychology department
for six years and then I moved to
Toronto and I've been here since 19 1998
I also do consulting work for a variety
of different companies now that's what
you're currently working on now probably
the most widely read book on psychology
for the novice reader was Jung's
masterpiece man and his symbols are you
approaching a general audience with this
book or your book maps of meaning or is
this more suited to the student of
psychology well I think it's suited for
people who would like a book like man
and his symbols and Jung's books even
the ones that were written for a general
audience were not particularly simple
because they're so different in
conception but I would say maps of
meaning is aimed at the same audience
that those books were aimed at now
they're similar to two books by Eric
Newman who was a very astute student of
Jung's and who took gills thought
farther in some directions than Jung
himself had so I guess I see my work in
part as an extension of Jung's work and
Newman's work partly into the domain of
neuropsychology and of course you could
say that you've led on from the workers
of luminaries such as look when we can
Stein with his book philosophical
investigations in 1953 for instance
where again he attempted to lay out the
apparent structure of the mind and the
conditioning with cultural and
historical variables would that be true
to say you've moved on from that and
expanded it even more one of it contains
contributions was the idea that a word
was more like a piece in a chess game
than it was like a label for an object
and prefer Wittgenstein's perspective
words were always to do things with
rather than to label things with and
that's a conception that I share because
most of our concepts scientists like to
think that our concepts are very much
like theories about objects but in
reality our concepts are much more
action-oriented than that I mean we know
for example that when you look at even a
simple object like a cup the brain areas
that are involved in motor action are
activated at the level of perception so
for example when you look at a cup the
gripping action that your hand would
make if you lifted up the cup is
partially activated merely when your
eyes settle on the cup itself so an
Vidkun Stein was the first philosopher
although Nietzsche knew this to some
degree to that consent was the first
philosopher to really point out the
functional quality of our object
categories and my work overlaps with his
ideas to some degree because uh one of
my preconceptions is that mythological
ideals ideas and concepts are functional
they're to do things with their to act
about they're not to label they're not
descriptive like a scientific concept is
that's why religious mythology has to do
with morality because morality is about
action in psychology what role does the
study of myth and symbols play and what
is the relationship to human
consciousness in say the treatment of
mental illness for instance or what we
class or classify in the Western concept
as mental illness well let's let's start
the first question about dreams I mean
there's a lot of debate in the
scientific literature about the meaning
of dreams
and perhaps there's even debate about
whether it's possible for dreams to have
meaning I think partly the debate exists
because to do dream analysis properly as
Union particular point it out you need a
vast body of knowledge in the dream
interpreter about comparative mythology
and ritual and symbol and and art
history and so forth because dreams of
course use images as their primary means
of conceptualization now in order to
understand what what dreams mean and how
they can be useful in therapy apart from
appreciating the fact that the
interpreter needs a broad body of
knowledge that scientists generally
don't develop it's also important to
know what it is that scientists have
discovered about dreams so for example
we know that dreams occur during rapid
eye movement sleep you cycle into rapid
eye movement sleep about every 90
minutes when you're asleep when you're
in rapid eye movement sleep your motor
centers so your action centers are very
much activated in your brain but your
body is paralyzed so that you can't move
around your eyes are moving because of
course it doesn't really matter if your
eyes move while you're asleep because
they won't take you anywhere but if your
legs were moving while you were asleep
you run into walls while you were
dreaming and scientists have actually
managed to damage the motor inhibition
systems in cats so that they do move
around when they're dreaming anyways if
you wake up when someone's dreaming
their brain is about as active as it is
when they're awake so there's a
tremendous amount of journal processing
going on in the dream state if you wake
someone up when they're dreaming there's
about an 80% chance that they'll report
the emotion of anxiety
dreams tend to focus on threat
processing now a threat is anything that
might hurt you but it's more than that -
a threat is anything that doesn't fit
into your current conceptual scheme you
imagine that you have a theory about the
way the world is and then you act on
that theory and sometimes things work
out the way you'd like them to work out
but often they don't and every time
things work out in a way that isn't how
you would like or how you predicted that
indicates that there's some more about
the world that you have to learn about
and that fact first manifests itself in
anxiety now the dream focuses on anxiety
and then it loosens up it's the normal
conceptual constraints that characterize
waking thinking and it starts to play in
a sense or hypothesize about how your
current categorical structure could be
shifted around so that that threat could
be accounted for
okay now that means the dream is dealing
with things that you need to understand
but you don't yet understand so when you
wake up and you remember the dream the
dream doesn't really make sense because
it's about something you don't
understand
now it's your brains best guess at
configuring or understanding the
unknowable but it's like it's it's like
the first layer of a multi-layered
process which eventually would culminate
in fully developed thought maybe over
months or maybe over years or maybe you
would never manage it at all the unknown
thing or the threat is just too great to
really come to any terms with it
whatsoever okay now I imagine that
you're dreaming about something and it
produces enough emotion what the threat
produces enough emotion not only to
produce a very vivid dream but to wake
you up when you wake up you remember the
dream and then you will tell someone
about it well the dream is about
something you don't yet understand that
that's upsetting and if you tell a bunch
of people about it they're going to give
you all sorts of opinions on the dream
that's a way that you can gather more
information about the threat are we
talking about an extreme case which is
known as a nightmare or perhaps simply a
dream which is faintly troubling all
puzzling because it's so abstract could
you differentiate between I think I
think it's clearer in the case of
nightmares and often too because
nightmares tend to have archetypal
themes you know people for example are
often threatened by monsters in
nightmares and a monster is a chimera
that's made up of the different parts of
different parts of frightening things a
dragon is a chimera for example because
it's made out of reptilian parts and it
also includes the idea of fire and
transformation so a nightmare is a dream
that tends to use archetypal imagery to
conceptualize a fairly powerful threat
and if you recount a nightmare to a
person with no specific training they're
going to have some opinion about it and
their opinion might be useful in terms
of information catherine but if you
recount a dream to someone who's
psychologically trained and is also
symbolically trained and who has you
know great great depth of knowledge with
regards to the structure of religious
thinking and and comparative literature
the light that they're going to shed on
your dream is much brighter and and more
profound and sometimes a dream
interpretation can offer the person
who's had the dream a leap forward in
knowledge that might have taken them
five or six years to conceptualize by
themselves an insight you might say that
they wouldn't normally have had because
the person who's the expert who's had
the dream recounted to them knows and
says ah yes I know of that place that
they say they've been to that experience
they've had that symbol and it's meaning
and above all what it feels like because
surely it is some people say that me
included that one way to interpret a
dream when you wake up is to just like
you would taste a sip of wine just hold
the
flavor and hold the feeling what does it
feel like
and what does fear what feels the same
in your real life and that's what the
dream is trying to tell you with a
collage of symbols and memories as well
that it's drawn on in recent conscious
experience to try and put it together
hence the dream can be very abstract
would you say that's the case sometimes
well I think there's two things about
about your comments that are are really
worth highlighting the first is the
category is that a dream uses are
generally based on emotional similarity
rather than logical similarity yes so a
dream for example might represent fear
or the fear of something unknown by
using a juxtaposition of a variety of
images of frightening things so imagine
that in the dream world the basic rule
is all things that produce the same
emotion are the same thing
and so your description of a dream
interpretation process that relies on
identifying similarities in emotional
state gets right to the core of how
dream thought works now secondarily I
also believe that if you are able to
help someone
construct a dream interpretation that
fits they're also able to feel that it
fits it clicks or it makes sense or it's
like the punchline of a joke in some way
they can tell that the interpretation
has put some missing pieces of the
puzzle into place and I think it's
important to rely on that as an
indicator of whether the interpretation
is actually derived from the dream or
sort of just a theoretical imposition on
its structure now we can go underneath
that too and and I mentioned already
that basic categories are more
action-oriented than object-oriented so
basic categories the basic categories of
the human mind are categories to do
things with well by the same token there
are also motivational and emotional
categories so the primordial mind like
the animal mind
thinks sort of axiomatically that all
things that produce the same emotion are
the same thing so there's things that
make you happy or there's things that
make you sad or there's things that make
you anxious and the fact that all those
things share the capacity to evoke that
emotion speaks of some ESET essential
identity between them now the identity
is in relationship to the experiencer
and not necessarily with regards to
similarity between the objects but it's
still how we naturally think and it's
certainly how mythology thinks and it's
how drama thinks and how religion thinks
and we've lost sight of that in part
because we've become scientifically
trained to some degree and we tend to
believe that the real categories of the
world are objective and alright that
that just strikes me as it's wrong
there's something about it that's wrong
and it's wrong because we have to act
sure there's something missing there
maybe we've lost it along the way going
back to emotional reactions people call
them knee-jerk response for instance if
you take the base emotions she only one
could go way way back to the dawn of our
beginnings when we came down from the
trees and move through the forest out
onto the plains under gatherers and
animals do share this with us because
the everyday dog and cat does have
emotions our emotions born out of
originally just pure instinct is this
where emotions came from do you think
because instinct causes reaction you
have the old adage of fight or flight
for instance depending on what you make
a decision to do okay so let's make a
conceptual definition here so that we
agree on the terminology let's say that
motivations are states of being that
indicate a goal that are indicative of a
goal so for example if you get hungry I
would say that's a motivational state
rather than an emotional
State and it's a motivational state that
sets the acquisition and ingestion of
food as the goal all right and so
there's a variety of motivational states
hunger thirst sexual desire generation
especially defensive aggression
predatory aggression and the desire to
eliminate essentially the desire to play
those are all motivational states and
then there's emotional states and the
primary emotional states are positive
and negative and positive emotional
states are experienced when you're
moving towards a desired goal and
negative emotional states occur when the
goal becomes uncertain or the pursuit is
somehow frustrated or or interfered with
okay now you asked about instincts well
I would say both motivations and
emotions are instincts they're very very
archaic
if you think about the positive and
negative emotions as being approach
versus withdrawal animals going all the
way back to single-celled organisms have
approached versus withdrawal symptoms so
they're unbelievably archaic they go way
back before we split evolutionarily from
our chimpanzee like ancestors so they
are instinct and they're very deep and
they the fact that those instincts exist
has all sorts of strange and that their
evolutionary based have all has all
sorts of strange implications so for
example you can understand the dog and
communicate with a dog because the dog
shares motivational and emotional
structure with you to great degree it's
a pack animal it knows about dominance
it knows about dominance striving it
feels anxiety and pain and it knows how
to play and it likes to play and there's
a lot about a human being and the dog
they're the same which is why we can
live together but you can go way down
the evolutionary chain so say if you go
all the way down to lobsters
lobsters know about dominance
hierarchies and they have approach and
withdrawal systems and the lobster
nervous system which is very primitive
compared to the human nervous system is
so similar to ours that you can give
lobsters antidepressants and it stops
them from feeling hurt after they've
been defeated in a physical dominance
dispute is that right yeah it's
absolutely amazing so typically if two
lobsters are in a dominus dispute and
one loses it will withdraw and then
it'll it kind of folds its body up it it
goes into a depressed like Crouch
whereas the winner will expand his body
and look bigger okay and when the
lobster is defeated it won't fight with
any other lobster for at least 20
minutes even one of it had defeated
before but if you give it
antidepressants in the aftermath of its
defeat it doesn't contract plus it will
fight right away it just well it just
shows you the idea of evolutionarily
determined instincts in my opinion is
not a theory at all it's an absolutely
self-evident fact and it manifests
itself in all sorts of strange ways so
for example we know with chimpanzees
chimpanzees basically go to war there
they're wired up to regard chimpanzee
conspecifics who aren't in their tribe
as something to react against with fear
and hostility and if a wandering group
of chimpanzees say numbering 3 or 4 at
the periphery of their territory comes
across an isolated individual or two
from another group they'll tear them
into shreds and that that primordial
response to the stranger sheds
substantial light on how it is that
human beings demonize and then persecute
their so-called enemies so we still
we've still retained this ability to
obtain
to fire a target for our resentment our
our hatred and our fear as well and that
can be demonization as you say is that
correct well part of it we could immune
can break it up into two two aspects I
think and this is something I go into
great detail about in maps of meaning in
some sense this is what the book is
about because I was interested in
territoriality and cruelty and now
animals are territorial and if another
animal of the same species trespasses on
to a complex animals territory there'll
be a fight and I think that's really
understandable because animals need
territory and human beings are clearly
territorial we're territorial about our
actual physical space and we're also
territorial about our ideological or
cultural space and it's because we need
to inhabit a physical territory and we
need to inhabit an ideological territory
and we react to challenges to the
integrity of our territory with fear and
with defensive aggression and I think
that can be understood quite
appropriately using analogs from animal
behavior and animal neural physiology
but you talked about resentment and
hatred
well those emotions I think are much
more specifically human there's lots of
examples from 20th century history of
the persecution of enemies going far
beyond what was merely needed to ensure
territorial integrity examples of course
of that sort of behavior abound in the
Holocaust literature where the Nazis
went out of their way not only to
eradicate the Jews and the gypsies and
so forth but to torment them and torture
them and crush them in ways that were
even that weren't even in the best
interests of the persecutor and that's a
lot more difficult to understand sure I
mean he had the ability to be able to
conceptually
dehumanized them to treat them as no
better than animals or intervention as
they called them but not forgetting that
there were earlier examples before in
the Holocaust in terms of numbers
sure and its scale and its
cold-bloodedness but if we go back to
times of say one of the earlier ones
tyrants that I thought were horrific was
Vlad the Impaler who used to enjoy
sitting eating his breakfast and having
his victims impaled before him and
that's psychopathic really is there
difference between that and say the
crimes of the narcy's well I don't think
there's a particular difference between
that and the crimes of the Nazis and I
also think that kind of behavior is far
more normative than anybody ever likes
to think I mean our in in in modern
times the Holocaust is sort of become
archetypal of totalitarian evil more
than just brutality but my sense after
having researched this for for a lengthy
period of time is that the hope the
behavior that characterized people who
were involved in the Holocaust was uh
essentially normative and even in 20th
century history the numbers that the
numbers involved in the Holocaust per se
aren't of any order of magnitude they're
they're not special they're not they're
not immense by any stretch of the
imagination
Solzhenitsyn estimated that Stalin's
brutality killed something in the
neighborhood of 60 million people shul
and there's estimates from Mao that he
killed a hundred million people hmm and
in Cambodia we know that at least four
million people died with the Khmer Rouge
yes so I mean like the Holocaust is is
the the prime exemplar of that kind of
behavior but it typifies the 20th
century and as you already pointed out
it's not my
rose in the twentieth century it's part
of our it's part of our nature but what
about the different what's the
difference between someone who would be
a concentration guard concentration camp
card who who would put these appalled
victims into the gas chamber or the guy
who pressed the release button on the
first atomic bomb from that aircraft
that he knew would slaughter thousands
or hundreds of thousands of people
because both those two people believed
in something is this where it really
boils down to the difference between
good and evil I think people use their
their claim that they believe in
something - look people will protect
what they believe in using the same
mechanisms that they'll protect
territory so for example if you own your
house and someone walks into it at night
under English common law you have the
right to say leave and then you have the
right to say leave I have a gun and then
you have the right to say leave I have a
gun and fire a warning shot and then if
they don't leave you have the right to
shoot them and you can't be prosecuted
for that okay and everyone would say
well you are within your rights because
you were protecting your territory okay
so I think people have a right to
protect their territory and they have a
right to protect their ideological
territory and there is rules of
engagement that could govern disputes of
that nature but when you're there's
there's other sorts of acts and many of
those characterized behavior in the
concentration camps in the Nazi era that
can't be explained by mere
territoriality and that's when it's
necessary as far as I'm concerned to
bring in conceptions derive from
mythology like the difference between
good and evil and I think that you can
define evil and evil is an act that is
designed to produce a negative outcome
for everyone who's involved
at that includes the victim and the
perpetrator sure but where does evil
come from in your concept of this well
dissipation is external reason why it's
very useful to look at mythology because
if you look at the first few chapters in
Genesis is a very clear story so let me
tell you one of the stories it's really
worth knowing okay so as far as I'm
concerned when Adam and Eve eat the
fruit of the tree of the the knowledge
of good and evil their eyes open and the
first thing that happens is that they
notice that they're naked okay so what
does that mean it means they're
illuminated with regards to their own
vulnerable nature because to be naked
and to know you're naked is to be
exposed and vulnerable and to know it
and often people for example will dream
that they have been stripped naked in
front of a crowd it means their material
vulnerability is exposed for everyone to
see okay the first thing Adam and Eve do
once they discover that they're naked is
to clothe themselves
cover themselves up and human beings are
the only creatures that wear clothes and
clothes separate our vulnerability from
the natural and social worlds they're
protective in reality and their
protective symbolically all right the
next thing that happens is that God
comes walking through the garden in the
morning and he looks for Adam and Adam
is hiding behind a bush and God says
Adam where are you I'm used to walking
with you and Adam says I'm too afraid to
come out because I found out that I'm
naked and God says who told you that you
were naked and Adam blames the woman
okay so then you think well why would
Adam hide from God
all right so imagine God God symbolizes
a transcendent totality and this story
indicates that at some point in human
history there was an unbroken
relationship between the transcendent
tality and the individual but when the
individual became self-conscious that
totality was threatened so why does adam
hide well he knows he's naked and
vulnerable so he hides from he hides
from the demands of of destiny he hides
from what's best in himself because he
looks at himself and thinks I'm nothing
I'm weak I'm I can be easily hurt and
therefore when God calls I have to hide
well the next thing that happens is that
Adam and Eve are thrown out of paradise
and God says well life is going to be
difficult now okay that sets the issue
up the next chapter starts with the
birth of Cain and Abel now Cain and Abel
are the first two humans born in history
right because everything that happens in
the Garden of Eden is pre historical
human history starts with the fall of
man the rise of self-consciousness and
Cain and Abel are the first two humans
and they're symbolic of two attitudes
towards the revelation of vulnerability
now Abel is a shepherd and Cain raises
vegetables and they're both required to
make sacrifices to God okay now why
would you make a sacrifice well it's an
archaic idea you burn something smoke
rises up to heaven gods in heaven and he
can judge the quality of your sacrifice
by evaluating the smoke we think well
that's a very archaic idea and what
could a modern person do with that well
a modern person could give these archaic
people some credit first so let's say
why is God in heaven well it's because
when you look at the sky at night it
fills you with awe you see an unlimited
expanse of being and that's the closest
you get to directly experiencing the
unnameable totality
okay why should you make sacrifices to
God why would he be pleased with
sacrifices well I would say you already
know that because if I asked you
well what sacrifices have you made to
make things better in your life no doubt
you could immediately tell me now our
cake people had to act that out because
they didn't really have the
philosophical conceptions in verbalize
herbal form but they still had an
intuition that it was necessary to make
the right sacrifice in order to maintain
an appropriate relationship with the
totality of being okay so able make some
sacrifices and can make some sacrifices
now Abel takes the best things he has
and offers them to God so they're the
firstborn of his flock and the choicest
cuts of meat when Abel's called on to
make a sacrifice he doesn't hold
anything back he puts himself on the
line and he sacrifices courageously and
clearly and Cain by contrast he brings
in some ratty little you know wrinkly
old vegetables and sacrifices those so
God smiles on Abel sacrifices and frowns
on Cain so what does that mean well
Abel's making the right sacrifices so
everyone likes him is this his
Enterprises flourish he has good the
intimate relationships he he produces a
thriving family because he makes the
right decisions and Cain on the other
hand everything goes wrong for him so
this makes a mat it says in the Old
Testament his countenance falls what
does that mean
he gets bitter and resentful and angry
and depressed he's mad about how things
are turning out so he goes and he has a
little shot with God and he says look
you know I don't know what's going on
here I'm working myself to the bone I'm
making sacrifices left right and center
and everything is not turning out for me
like what gives and God says pay
attention here it's your problem that
things aren't going well
the the monster of sin crouches at your
door and you welcome it in you could
reject it you could do things right you
know exactly what the right thing to do
is yet you refuse to do it so all the
trouble you're having is your fault
don't come along and blame me just get
yourself put together properly and do
things right and so that's the end of
the conversation well that isn't what
Cain wants to hear he wants to hear that
the world's a miserable place and that
the reason that he's failing is is
because of the structure of reality he
doesn't want to hear that it's his
problem so this just makes them
absolutely boiling mat and the first
thing he does is go and kill Abel well
that's the difference between
territoriality and evil and he wants
what Abel has he wants to be able but
instead he destroys him out of spite and
resentment and revenge against the
nature of reality well then God gets
wind of it marks Cain he says no one
killed him and you might think well why
because it's God who says an eye for an
eye well the next little bit of the
story which is barely there anymore it's
it's so edited out explains exactly why
Cain wanders away and he gets married
and he has a family but if you mess
around with any of Cain's family if you
annoy them or bother them or make them
resentful or angry they don't just kill
one person they kill seven and then
those children have children and if you
annoy them they kill 70 and at the end
of that acceleration of revenge oriented
killing God comes along and floods
everything that's when this story of
Noah and the Ark kicks in and the story
is very clear it says this if you act
improperly and if you do the things that
you know to be wrong if you don't make
the right sacrifices your life will not
turn out well you'll be punished all the
time for your foolishness and your
weakness and that will make you
resentful twisted bitter and murderous
when you act on those motivations
because of spite and resentment you'll
you'll initiate a cataclysm of revenge
oriented killings and if no stop is put
to them that will spread through the
entire society and invite the apocalypse
and that's the second third major story
in Genesis do this actly right mmm
listen some very very strong would you
call it moral teaching there or is it
more than that
I mean whoever wrote at the inside is
moral for sure you know I mean because
it but it's it's moral in a weird way
you know it's it's it's more like a
description of moral reality than a
story that says well you should act like
this because that would be good
it's imagine this story of Cain and Abel
this is a really old story it's been
around for we have no idea how long in
written form it's been around for
several thousand years it's undoubtedly
part of a larger oral tradition it was
edited by many many people and told and
retold and all that's left of that story
is what's intensely memorable because
otherwise it wouldn't have been
forgotten and it just says something
blatantly it says that you can accept
your you can accept the need to make
sacrifices in order to keep your life on
the right track or you can fight against
that and act improperly if you fight
against that and act improperly then
you're going to compromise your
relationship with the totality of being
and as soon as you do that you might as
well essentially you're living in a hell
if you if you subject yourself
chronically to a hellish existence that
will make you turn your thoughts towards
really towards revenge against existence
itself
well you know stellen was setting
himself up to blow up the entire planet
and there's good evidence from the KGB
archives in the late 1950s that he was
gearing up with his multiple free
pre-apocalyptic genocide 'old practices
he was gearing up enough courage to turn
the whole world into a conflagration
well this is no a trivial matter and the
only stories that I know that have
enough profundity to lay out the real
seriousness of the issue are these
archaic stories nothing in modern
culture has the requisite profundity now
we're just pausing for some exciting
news about Austrian magazine calm stay
with us by the way don't forget to grab
your own copy of our fascinating 40 page
Austria magazine just visit our magazine
web page at www.rockymountainatvmc.com
is full of fresh news information
articles free audio interviews your very
own copy of the latest issue of Austrian
magazine and also we have a message
board if you want to leave your own news
or discuss some of the articles with
other people from across the Internet ww
austria magazine calm
this is no trivial matter and the only
stories that I know that have enough
profundity to lay out the real
seriousness of the issue are these
archaic stories nothing in modern
culture has the requisite profundity
sure we have we do have sayings such as
you get out of life what you put into it
and another one that comes to mind is he
who lives by the sword dies by the sword
in the east they have their concept of
and tradition of karma yeah well karma
karma is a karma is a really good
example because the idea behind karma
it's very interesting I think from a
neuropsychological perspective because
karma is predicated on the idea that it
is fundamentally impossible for you to
get away with anything but and there's
an idea in Christianity that's like that
too it's a little more archaic and more
dramatic than the idea of karma the idea
in Christianity is that all of your
actions and motivations are in some
manner recorded and that you'll be
brought to task for them but and modern
people look at that especially when it's
represented metaphorically as say a wise
old man writing in a book and they just
discounted entirely but I've certainly
come to believe as a consequence of
studying what I've studied that you you
it is absolutely impossible for you to
get away with anything whenever you make
a mistake and you know it's a mistake
you will eventually pay for it you might
not notice that that's what you're
paying for because often the punishment
and the crime are so distant in time
from one another that the causal
connection is virtually impossible to
identify but that doesn't mean it isn't
there now one of the things I attempted
to lay out in maps of meaning in some
detail with Solzhenitsyn's insights into
a
the processes that led to the
establishment of the Gulag Archipelago
prison camps in the soviet union where
so many tens of millions of people were
killed
it was Solzhenitsyn's belief and this is
a belief that young Sheridan and as well
Eric Newman that it was the cumulative
sins of the individuals that made up a
population that culminated in these
absolute totalitarian catastrophes so
just as Kane's unwillingness to make the
appropriate sacrifices in his individual
day-to-day life culminated in the
degeneration of his entire society and
the and the and the and the bringing
forth of an apocalypse
so in everyday life each individual
moral errors accumulate and manifest
themselves at a social level and play
themselves out in this immense in this
immense forum now we don't like to think
that way because no individual likes to
feel that they're localized foolishness
and weakness conscious foolishness and
weakness reverberates through the entire
social structure but everything that
I've ever read that was serious with
regards to this kind of subject
indicated precisely that I mean even
Hannah Arendt she wrote ah the banality
of evil well you know I think it's the
evil of banality personally but she
cheek the the the architect of the of
the final solution was a leak negligible
resentful nonentity and what that shows
you is just how horrifying it is morally
to be a weak resentful judgmental
nonentity it's it's so catastrophic ly
wrong
under the appropriate conditions it can
endanger the structure of being going on
to another thesis of yours in maps of
meaning you talk about the fact that
we're comfortable with the known what is
known around which we build all our
cultural traditions and from which our
myths are propagated and then this
exploration of the new if you like and
how we can act on that could you tell us
a bit more about that because you're
insinuating I believe in your your work
that in your book that to do so can make
one some kind of a it's some kind of
heroic action you you've mapped out
something whereby we can reach out for
what is unknown to explore our potential
and creativity is that correct that I
think that's a good summary
I mean imagine imagine that in life you
have you have some one obvious thing to
rely on an obvious thing you have to
rely on is the traditional knowledge and
wealth of your culture it contains most
of the knowledge that you have and
allows you to make your life as
comfortable as it has been made within
it but there are other sources of
strength too and they're more subtle so
your culture provides you with what's
known and what's knowable but culture is
never mapped everything out perfectly
there's many things that remain to be to
be known and many of the things that
remain to be known are valuable and what
that means is that if you search after
what is yet unknown
you can also derive strength from that
because that's the domain in which new
discoveries are made and so if I face
you with evidence that you're wrong
about something which means there's
something that you don't know that
you're not taking into account that can
frighten you because it shows you that
the knowledge structures that you rely
on are dangerously incomplete and that
can make you very angry and that can
make you very resentful or you can say
always in fact so fascinating the fact
that something isn't known here means
that I could go and discover that I
could voluntarily encounter that and I
could derive something new and valuable
and I could use that and the hero in
mythology is the person who voluntarily
encounters the unknown and and this is a
unbelievably old concept it's the oldest
concept we know that human beings have
created it stems all the way back to the
ANU MELAS the Mesopotamian creation myth
which is the oldest written document we
have and it's the enumeration is the
story on which the first story in
Genesis is based now here here's a way
of thinking about things and this is a
mythological way and it's extremely
useful so forget for a minute the idea
that the world is made out of matter and
forget that it's made out of objects
look at it from a different perspective
we'll say the world of experience which
is the world you inhabit is made out of
three things it's made out of the fact
that no matter how much you know there
are going to be phenomena and
occurrences that exceed your capacity
for comprehension and that's always
going to be the case and so we're going
to call that a category that's the
category of the unknown and then there
are always going to be things that you
know and understand and that's part of
your tradition we're going to call that
the known so wherever you go wherever
you are there's a balance between the
known and the unknown and then the third
thing is the fact of you there's a
conscious observer there and the
conscious observer is the place where
the known and the unknown interact
that's the mythological actors the known
that's the Great Father the unknown
that's the great mother and the
individual and the Daoists represent
that as yin and yang or chaos versus
order people think about that as
masculine versus feminine that gives us
a bad interpretation or
insufficient interpretation of taoist
thought the taoist say experience is
made of chaos and order and the proper
place to stand is right between them and
you can tell when you're standing right
between chaos and order because that's
when you feel that things are meaningful
and that means that meaning is the
instinct that tells you that you're
standing in the right place now people
are vulnerable and they're afraid
because of that and they can be
challenged and hurt and they can be made
angry and murderous but I would say well
if you stand between chaos and order
properly your life can become so
meaningful that the meaning gives you
confidence and power and the ability to
overcome your sense of shameful
vulnerability and I would also say
that's what religious stories are
telling you to do now we go back to
Genesis in the beginning God makes order
out of chaos and that story is based on
an order architecture derived from the
ANU male ish in the anu male ish a god
named Marduk cuts up the dragon of chaos
and makes the world out of her pieces
well the dragon of chaos recurs as a
mythological motif frequently generally
in the guise of Leviathan say and yahwah
is envisioned as the deity that derives
order habitable order from chaos and
immediately after yahwah derives
habitable order from chaos he announces
he makes human beings and then he
announces that they are made in his
image male and female made in his image
what we think that means that God is
like a human being but what it really
means is that the human being is like
God in that the human being has the
capacity to make order out of chaos and
when we say that there's something
divine about a person that gives them
intrinsic rights what we mean is the
fact that each human being can make
order out of chaos means that every
single person is deserving of a certain
kind of respect even if their murderous
even if they're criminals even if their
prostitutes are tax collectors they're
still they're still embodied with it the
kind of dignity that only identity with
God can provide and that identity is the
capacity to make order out of chaos
and it's not just a metaphor mm-hmm what
about the people who of the extreme
criminals of whom which said they had no
conscience or their conscience is dead
what's happened with those sort of
individuals is it so just very
suppressed or has it really died
something in them died a spark gone ELPS
well you know that that's such that's
such a difficult question you know
because we know for example that certain
kinds of extreme brain damage can cause
a kind of criminal behavior so for
example if your prefrontal cortex is
damaged then that can make you impulsive
in criminal and so from a scientific
perspective I would say it's very
difficult to judge the culpability of
certain people because they've been
damaged in some way we don't really
understand and so the limits on their
capacity to choose are compromised and
it's very it's a it's a situation that
has to be judged carefully in each
individual case but then mythologically
I would say what Solzhenitsyn said and
what he said was that in every person no
matter how good there is a little corner
of corruption and evil that still hasn't
been overcome and then in every one no
matter how evil and corrupt there's a
little bit of a little corner of good
that's still a possibility that might be
made to manifest itself and I don't
exactly know how to reconcile those two
different viewpoints you know and I
think I think each of them are right
even though their juxtaposition makes
them makes a paradox
now so looking at peridot it was like I
read about Ted Bundy mmm you know about
Ted Bundy goons and it was a law student
in um in the u.s. very good-looking
young man and he raped and murdered a a
number of young women and one of his
tricks was to put on a fake cast and to
elicit a sympathetic to stop someone
someone young and beautiful who is
driving a vehicle to use their sympathy
as a means of getting them compromised
he was a terrible person but I read
about his journey downhill you know and
he said he first started to get involved
in violent pornography and that as far
as he was concerned that was what opened
the door and I think that's a good
metaphor I mean one of the things you
talked about continually when he was
attempting to explain what had happened
in Nazi Germany was the fact that a
person moving moving downhill to some
horrific end point like a concentration
camp guards say makes a little mistake
knows it's a mistake makes a little
mistake little compromise and that puts
them in a position where another
compromise is more likely and then that
puts them in a position where another
compromise is more likely and 300
compromises later is there's a great
book called ordinary man it's a study of
a Police Battalion in Poland and these
men started out as normal middle-aged
policemen most of them adults before
Hitler even came to power so not victims
of Hitlerian propaganda in their
maturing phase they went from perfectly
ordinary policemen two men who were
taking naked pregnant women out into
fields and shooting them behind the head
and the book details their descent into
this hellish place step by step
well I think that's how people descent
you know it's step by step and I believe
under most circumstances that every step
is conscious even though the memory of
making this step might fade into
unconsciousness and the full cataclysmic
consequences of each moral error aren't
necessarily evident so what happens in
the case of looking at the individual as
opposed to the group consciousness very
quickly when someone has what's known as
a nervous breakdown is that when they
just can't make order out of anything
they just can't cope
they just withdrawal sure that I mean
what we could look at that neural
psychologically or we could look at it
descriptively so here's what happens
neural psychologically there is a little
brain organ called the hippocampus and
the hippocampus helps you know where you
are and what you're doing and it
inhibits a whole array of more
primordial emotional structures
particularly the amygdala and the
hypothalamus now the amygdala is
responsible for anxiety and fear and the
hypothalamus is responsible for all
different kinds of motivation now as
long as you know where you are and what
you're doing which means that when you
act the outcome you desire occurs
because that sort of defines knowing
where you are and what you're doing then
the amygdala and the hypothalamus remain
inhibited now as soon as things aren't
turning out the way you expect them to
then the amygdala is disinhibited and so
is the hypothalamus and then the hypo
then you get afraid and paralyzed and
the hypothalamus starts to produce a
stress hormone called cortisol now
cortisol is in some ways a stimulant
it'll stimulate exploratory behavior and
in small doses it's pretty good for you
but in large doses it hyper activates
your physiology shuts off your immune
system it compromises your long-term car
the bility and it's toxic it starts to
destroy the hippocampus and as it
destroys the hippocampus the ability of
the hippocampus to inhibit your negative
emotional responses is increasingly
compromised and that turns into a cycle
and if the cycle gets instantiated with
enough intensity then the entire
negative emotional system can get dis in
evident and the knowledge structure
start start to become demolished and
when people talk about a nervous
breakdown which is usually a
post-traumatic stress disorder chronic
repeating depression that's basically
what they're talking about which is why
if you have a conversation with someone
who goes through regular bouts of
depression their perception of reality
is distorted they just see everything
negative about anything you can think
about yeah well and what happens is you
may imagine imagine if you're doing some
small tasks oh let's say you're cutting
up broccoli for dinner and you you cut
your finger and I say to you what is
what is the fact that you cut your
finger mean here's some possibilities it
means you should be more careful when
you're cutting broccoli it means that
you're actually not very careful the
fact that you're not very careful about
cutting broccoli indicates you're
probably not as careful as you should be
about most things you do the fact that
you're doing is careful about most
things you do as you should be is an
explanation for why all the things that
have gone wrong in your life up to this
point have actually gone wrong people
like you who have had lots of good of
things go wrong and who aren't
sufficiently careful tend to go downhill
over time plus they're very not very
good people maybe they shouldn't even be
around
okay that's how a depressed person
thinks she will not said quite a
wide-scale there isn't that well what
happens is that their ability to inhibit
the spread of the meaning of the
negative event is completely compromised
because they're nervous their nervous
system has it's there supposed to be a
threshold for the transmission of
negative information across different
levels of abstraction
you're supposed to be somewhat resistant
to that spread you know it could easily
be that it could easily be true that the
fact that you cut yourself is an
indication that you're not living your
life properly but it isn't necessarily
the first conclusion that you should
leap to but for a depressed person you
know that's that's often inevitable they
can't help it yes they take on a sort of
downward slope a slippery slope now
moving on they're overwhelmed by chaos
yes the mythological explanation yes now
you were just at a major conference on
consciousness in Arizona I gather now
what new ideas did you see presented in
this field that you found interesting at
that conference well it's funny you know
this conference I've been to that
conference several times and I really
think the last time I went I had I
learned things that were more directly
relevant so let me give you let me give
an example of that instead it's a
researcher named Valen wieder who has
been investigating the mechanisms of
action of hallucinogenic drugs
hallucinogenic drugs have been used as
you know though throughout history to
produce mystical experiences of one form
or another and Voland wider actually
provided an explanation of why that
might be and that was very interesting
to me so yours when your your senses are
each somewhat independent systems but
the the content of your sensory
experience is unified in a brain area
called the thalamus now so imagine your
your sight and your vision and your
touch and your sense of your body in
space are all integrated in the thalamus
but there's a lot of information coming
in from all of your senses okay now
imagine that your prefrontal cortex
which is a relatively new part of the
brain
it sets up a plan what you're going to
do next and it tells the hypothalamus
only let information relevant to the
plan through into consciousness so for
example if you walk into the kitchen and
you're going to make yourself something
to eat you're not going to notice the
floor and you're not going to notice the
paint on the ceiling you're going to
notice the refrigerator and the stove
and the few implements that you need to
undertake the task related to eating so
the prefrontal cortex gates the Salamis
now there's a million things you could
pay attention to in the kitchen if the
kitchen is a very complex visual
environment if you take a hallucinogenic
drug it inhibits the prefrontal cortexes
capacity to gate the thalamus and all
sorts of sensory information flows
through now most of the time when you
look at the world you hardly see any of
it you filter it out yes exactly your
brain is exactly as Aldous Huxley
proposed your brain is actually a
sequence of extremely extremely complex
filtering mechanisms and most of what's
out there is eliminated well following
on volunter ground of mystical
experience is the partial apprehension
of the richness of potential experience
beyond beyond what's expected so when
you look at the world what you see is
mostly relevant to your current plan and
shape to a tremendous degree by your
memory and if if those systems are
inhibited or shut down in some way and
you have the opportunity to apprehend
what's actually there what this
sensation it produces
which is the disinhibition of certain
kinds of emotion is very much associated
with what people describe as aw no I
would say to here here's something
interesting in that regard you know
people say people ask themselves for
example do you believe in God and I
would say that's actually a nonsensical
question I would say whether or not you
believe in God you're more or less stuck
with him he's there whether you believe
it or not and it has nothing to do with
belief and I'll tell you why it's
actually straightforward okay so let's
go back to the ancient Israelis
Israelites now they had some rules they
believed that there was a unity behind
everything and that unity was unnameable
so it was against the rules to speak the
name of God why well because as soon as
you speak the name of something you
categorize it and it is its
categorizable and understandable then
it's not the totality it's something
you've parceled off and made into a
concept the totality of being is beyond
all conceptualization okay so then you
might ask yourself well is there a
totality of being well the answer to
that is well obviously because
everything there is sums up to one
totality well what's the nature of that
totality well it's unutterable you can't
say it's too complex it's too rich it's
it's not within human ability to grasp
is it there well it's there just like a
room contains the objects in the room
it's there for sure okay so there is a
totality that's unnameable the next
question would be well do you have a
relationship with it well the answer to
that is of course you have a
relationship with it because every part
has a relationship to the whole because
you're alive
basically well and then you're here in
Erie you're inside the totality now then
you might ask but what's the nature of
your relationship with that totality and
I would say well you tell me it's easy
to know is your life rich and meaningful
and worthy of sustaining and in your own
from your own perspective do you believe
that life is worthwhile you live it in a
manner that makes it worthwhile
and if answer that is yes then I would
say well you have the proper
relationship with the totality and if
answer is no you doubt the value of life
you're hostile and resentful you're
bored you're afraid you're hurt
well then there's something wrong with
your relationship with the totality well
what's what's so complicated about that
it's it's it's it's self-evident and
it's stunning to me that it's the
subject of so much constant dispute
now you might object well you have a
relationship with the totality but it's
not a personal relationship which is
what the ancient Israelites claimed and
of course what the Protestant
Protestants claimed even more
dramatically and I would say well you
could be right but let's consider it an
experiment here's the experiment try to
establish a personal relationship with
this totality and here's here's the
criteria I will say that whenever you're
doing something that's intensely
meaningful then you've established a
personal relationship with this totality
and if all you ever did were things that
were intensely personally meaningful
while you'd live an ideal life and you
wouldn't be afraid of death and you
wouldn't become bitter and resentful and
it's also doable I think with every
choice you make you decide whether
you're going to do that or not it's
difficult to do meaningful things
everybody doesn't always agree with them
they're kind of idiosyncratic there's no
necessary reason that you'll be rewarded
by the culture with material success if
you do meaningful things
so it's a shot in the dark it's a leap
of faith but it's right within your
grasp you can you can do it just by
deciding to well what I learned from
writing maps of meaning was that the
fate of the world literally depends on
the choice that each individual makes
with regards to their relationship to
the totality of being and that's that
and that's what that's the central
message of profound religious systems
says there's more to you than you think
a lot more there's more to more for evil
way more than you think and there's way
more for good and whether you know it or
not you're always choosing between those
two and whether you know it or not the
fate of being itself rests on your
choice well who the hell wants to
believe that exactly we do wait it's too
weighty well I don't care if it's
weighty or not when you're trying to
investigate the reasons behind something
like the Holocaust things get weighty
very rapidly
what about 9/11 the the shock of people
seeing that unfold on their TV screens
or people who were there now that was a
group experience it wasn't an individual
just purely individual experience how do
you think we handled that well I think
you can think of two recent events uh in
an illuminating way 9/11 would be one
and the flooding of New Orleans would be
another so with regards to 9/11 the most
interesting thing to note about people's
responses to that catastrophe was their
unconscious need for repetition I mean
everyone I know watched the Trade Towers
fall 50 times or a hundred times in
shark unable not to watch and I think
the reason that that's so illuminating
is because it shows you how complicated
it is to see what you don't understand
so mythologically speaking the fall of
the towers was equivalent both to the
death of the king and to the
re-emergence of chaos and when the King
dies and chaos Ria's it's very difficult
to see what's there and I'm not speaking
metaphorically precisely people wouldn't
have had to watch the Towers fall over
and over if they could see them fall and
on a trivial level a building collapsed
but what the events that characterized
9/11 were far more than merely a
building falling when the event happened
no one knew what fell no one knew if the
financial system fell no one knew if the
economic system fell no one knew if the
world order had collapsed and everyone
watching those buildings fall was trying
to perceive all those others of levels
of reality at the same time well that's
really really complicated well and then
Bush offered people and easy-out and a
prepared way out he said well the people
who did this were evil and perhaps they
were the people who did this were evil
we're good there should be a war now as
far as I'm concerned well that's a
mythological explanation and it's it's
it's very easy for people to instantly
put forth a mythological explanation
when chaos makes itself manifest well of
course the problem with our response to
9/11 was that air almost every bit of it
was a lie um we know that the American
government utilized the events of 9/11
to justify an invasion on Iraq that had
been planned at least 10 years before
the historical documentation of that is
is available from the people who did the
planning they're still part of Bush's
government
so you asked about our response
well you can't I mean I think when Bush
first went into Iraq people had a
legitimate debate about what should be
done about tyrants like Saddam Hussein
because he was obviously a horrible
person and his sons were even worse but
the idea that a catastrophe consisting
of the re-emergence of chaos could be
met by dissimulation and conscious lies
and that that would work out
successfully well that's I would say
that's willfully blind corrupt and naive
all at the same time and that's what
characterized our response right wasn't
that response plan by a group who
disciples and followers of a philosopher
called Strauss is that correct yes
that's right that's right and they had
put a manifesto together that are back
in the mid 1990s I mean the hope had
written Clinton you know are expressing
their their need to invade Iraq which
which I don't really think is the issue
like I said because Saddam Hussein was a
terrible person and it isn't clear that
the international community exactly
knows what to do with barbaric dictators
the problem wasn't necessarily the idea
that going after Saddam Hussein was
justified the problem was that an event
that had absolutely nothing to do with
him was utilized in an absolutely
deceitful manner by people who had a
preexistent agenda to deceive their
entire populace and to justify and to
use that as justification for doing
something that they had other reasons
for doing then they can win the seems
they can win the justification for
judging it seems that you have to be a
victor in order to be able to judge as
in Nuremberg the victors judged they've
judged as saying you know they put him
on trial
but otherwise as you said the world
community you don't seem to know what to
do otherwise with scenes power it's a
complicated problem right I mean it's
part of the problem we're talking about
this what's the appropriate response to
the manifestation of evil well I would
say generally speaking evil is something
best corralled in your own life and once
you more or less corralled it in your
own life if you have in fact managed out
because that is a very very difficult
thing to do well then maybe you have
something to say about it on a social
level but we we constant people put the
cart before the horse and many many
individuals who are unable to make peace
in their own house are perfectly willing
to go out and try to make peace in the
world well there's more it's an ideology
in that than there is intelligence and
and and caution and this is something
else you want to add about either maps
of meaning Jordan or whether you want to
talk more about new ideas you're working
on well there's just just one thing I
wanted to have I mentioned 9/11 and new
orally yes New Orleans is another
example of the death of the king and the
re-emergence of chaos being the same
thing the chaos in Genesis is watery and
it's watery chaos that causes floods and
the flood that God caused with regards
to Noah was the re-emergence of chaos
because of a corrupt social order well
the same thing happened in New Orleans
on the one hand it was a storm so the
storm caused the flooding but on the
other hand had the levees being four
feet higher there wouldn't have been a
catastrophe so the fact that there was a
flooded New Orleans is as much evidence
that order was insufficient to hold
chaos back as it is evidence that the
chaotic hand of God is perfectly capable
of causing natural disasters
there was too much disorder there on the
side of order exactly they're too much
and it was not just disorder but
corruption right so it's archaic
cultural systems they the levees they're
too old and starting to deteriorate so
there's a deteriorate of their own
accord plus the deterioration is sped
along by the fact that the people who
are putative Lee in charge of them
aren't taking the responsibilities
seriously on a similar matter for sure
on a similar basis it's not about
flooding but it that reminds me in
Australia on the in certain beaches that
have been shark attacks where they have
shark fences out in the in the sea which
have not been repaired and there are
holes in the fences and so sharks are
getting through and attacking surfers is
exactly the same the same right and
that's in fact you know I would say the
reason that example popped into your
mind is because of the mythological
equivalence you see because the
underwater creature the terrible human
devouring underwater creature is a prime
mythological representation of chaos so
for example time out in the ANU mulisch
who's basically the model for the
leviathan is an underwater dragon an
underwater devouring dragon and she's
this prime symbol of chaos and so I
would say your example was brought to
mind by the mythological equivalent
between the two between the two
occurrences well professor Peterson has
been a great pleasure hearing you
discuss your ideas and your work maps of
meaning could you please tell us where
this book is available well I would say
the simplest place to find it is at
Amazon if you go to my website which is
maps of meaning calm right there are
lectures on the book televised by
Canadian Public Television and links to
places the book can be purchased so
that's probably the simplest thing to do
okay and
what's your next project what are you
working on are you writing some more are
you concentrating on your your lecturing
or are you touring or what's happening
now well I've written recently a few
papers on the nature of self-deception
which is a very paradoxical concept
self-deception implies that at least in
its classical formulations that a person
knows something and doesn't know
something at the same time which is
problematic conceptually for a variety
of reasons I've been trying to crack
that problem I've also been attempting
to recast our models of
neuropsychological functioning
starting from the presupposition that
what the mind encounters is much more
properly conceptualized as an
information-rich matrix of relationships
than it is conceptualized as a place of
material objects and that's following to
some degree the ideas of the physicist
wheeler who is a student of Niels Bohr I
believe who who has hypothesized that
the fundamental elements of matter are
more like depth more like computer bits
of information than they are like
something classically material could
this explain how we they conducted
experiment experiments with quarks is it
in quantum physics where the observer
actually causes the event to happen well
it does seem related to that in some
manner and and I I believe that um that
idea is linked to the notion I described
earlier about the capacity of human
consciousness to make order out of chaos
like I personally believe and this is
partly because of what I've learned from
reading religious mythology that human
consciousness realizes the world in in
some non metaphorical sense I cried I
not a materialist and I truly believe
that if human consciousness did not
exist the idea that there would be
existence is is in some manner wrong I
think existence is dependent on
consciousness and I've been trying to
work out the implications of that idea
in a scientifically rigorous manner and
that constitutes partly what I've been
writing about recently
that sounds very very interesting and of
course we all take for granted if you or
I can sit here and talk about let's talk
about for instance think of the first
world war okay and we think that this
happened that happened etc you can think
about the Great Depression neither you
nor I were alive at the time Yeah right
but we take it for granted that it
happened yeah now if you go from now
today and you go forward a hundred years
neither you nor I will be alive then but
that shouldn't worry us should it well I
would say that the fact of our being
would still be embedded in the matrix of
reality right right we because the
things fold up in a way the past folds
up and is still present in the present
and the future is not yet unfolded
implicit in the present and I would say
just as none of your deeds do you just
as you cannot escape from the
consequences of any of your deeds the
record of your being and and the nature
of that being is embedded in the fabric
of reality permanently because possibly
what we conceive as a timeline is a
man-made abstraction maybe there is no
such thing as time
well there is for us and but what that
means in some ultimate sense is
obviously not our conceptually
accessible to us
I think that's part of the reason why
it's possible to realize that the
implications of your behavior and your
conceptions reverberate far past you
things are not necessarily precisely
what they seem like ripples on a on a
pond professor Turing Peterson it has
been marvelous discussing these subjects
with you and listening to your views I'm
sure our listeners will find this most
interesting and on behalf of all the
staff here at Austria magazine.com and
Austria web radio I'd like to extend our
thanks and we hope that you'd be able to
submit an article for us at some stage
if you wish for our magazine in the due
course of time and maybe you'd like to
come back for another discussion at some
point in the future but on behalf of
everyone here thank you very much for
this most fascinating discussion thanks
very much for the opportunity thank you
professor Jordan Peterson author of maps
of meaning well that brings us to the
end of this show thanks for listening
and we hope you enjoyed it do join us
regularly for all the latest ideas news
reviews and discussions and free audio
downloads all here at Austria magazine
web radio you'll right click to
knowledge and discovery you might also
want to download our feature-packed
Austria magazine Austria magazine has
got 40 pages of high-quality articles by
well-known authors scholars and
progressive thinkers and it only costs a
trifling three pound sterling or a
couple of dollars or so simply purchase
your download via our secure protective
paypal system and it's yours to print
out and keep we're sure you'll have
hours and hours of enjoyment and
fascination reading Astraea magazine so
just go to our magazine page and grab
your very own copy
ww austria magazine calm